A Guide to the Page Family Papers, 1819-1976
Virginia Historical Society
Virginia Historical Society
A Guide to the Page Family Papers, 1819-1876
Virginia Historical Society
Mss1 P1456 a FA2
2,050 (ca.)items (18 manuscipt boxes)
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. William Maury Hill, Richmond, Va., in 1989. Accessioned June 26, 1996.
Biographical/Historical Information
Records of four generations of the Page family of Hanover County and Richmond, Va., and related families. Represented are Francis Page (1780-1849); his son John Page (1821-1901) of "Oakland," Hanover County, a graduate of the University of Virginia, lawyer, and for four years an attorney for the Commonwealth in Hanover County; Elizabeth Burwell (Nelson) Page (1821-1912), wife of John Page and mother of Francis Page, Thomas Nelson Page, and Rosewell Page; Robert Nelson (1819-1886), Episcopal missionary to China and brother of Elizabeth Burwell (Nelson) Page; Robert's wife, Rose (Points) Nelson (1827-1885); Francis Page (1849- 1918), better known as "Frank," an Episcopal priest who served parishes in Virginia, Texas, and Brooklyn, N.Y.; Thomas Nelson Page (1853-1922) of Richmond, Va., Washington, D.C., and York Harbor, Me., lawyer, lecturer and writer, and U.S. Ambassador to Italy from 1912-1918; Anne Seddon (Bruce) Page (1867-1888), first wife of Thomas Nelson Page and originally from "Staunton Hill," Charlotte County, Va.; Florence (Lathrop) Field Page (1858-1921), first married to Henry Field (brother of Marshall Field) and then married in 1893 to Thomas Nelson Page; Rosewell Page (1858-1939) of "Oakland," Hanover County, lawyer in Richmond, writer, member of the General Assembly of Virginia, and second auditor of Virginia from 1912-1928; Ruth (Nelson) Page (1871-1975?), second wife of Rosewell Page; Anne (Page) Johns (b. 1899) of Richmond, daughter of Rosewell and Ruth (Nelson) Page; Frank Stoddert Johns (1884-1971), Anne (Page) Johns' husband; and Julien Harrison Hill (1877-1943), banker in Richmond and father-in-law of Ruth Nelson (Johns) Hill, daughter of Anne (Page) Johns and Frank Stoddert Johns; and Lucy Colder De Lancey (Kearny) Hill (b. 1881), wife of Julien Harrison Hill. Also included are scattered correspondence of the Bruce, Field, Johns, Lathrop, Nelson, and Points families, and Page cousins.
Scope and Content Information
Series 1 of the collection begins with the papers of Francis Page (1780-1849), consisting of two receipts, one for the digging of a well (1819) and one for his subscription to the National Vaccine Institution (1825).
Series 2 contains the papers of John Page (1821-1901) of "Oakland," Hanover County, Va., and consist of correspondence, 1877-1898. Principal correspondents are his wife, Elizabeth Burwell (Nelson) Page, and his sons, Rosewell Page and Thomas Nelson Page. One of the few letters in the collection written by Rosewell as he practiced law in Danville, Va., is in this series. Letters by John Page to his son Thomas discuss family activity, political and business tasks that the father wants the son to handle in Richmond, Va., business and personal advice, and news of the crops at "Oakland."
Elizabeth Burwell (Nelson) Page (1821-1912) materials follow in Series 3. Page, of "Oakland," Hanover County, Va., kept a diary, 1905, recording activities for each day. Entries describe the farm activities at "Oakland," the servants and their roles, local epidemics of smallpox, and the lives of her son, Rosewell Page, and his wife, Ruth (Nelson) Page, who lived at "Oakland," including frequent reference to Rosewell's role as a layman in the Episcopal Church, news of her other two sons, Francis (better known as Frank) Page, an Episcopal priest, and Thomas Nelson Page who occasionally visits "Oakland" and checks on his land holdings and mill operations in Hanover County, Va. Two pages of accounts are at the end of the diary and include references to servants' wages and farm expenses. Scattered accounts appear throughout the diary.
Also present are letters of Elizabeth Burwell (Nelson) Page, chiefly written to her middle son, Thomas Nelson Page, from 1876 to 1912. Elizabeth wrote primarily from "Oakland," Hanover County, Va., but also while visiting her sister, Virginia Lafayette (Nelson) Nelson, in Charlottesville. Her letters to Thomas are addressed to numerous locations around the United States, especially New York and York, Maine, and in Europe. In them, Elizabeth discusses her daily activities on the farm at "Oakland" and the activities of other family members such as her brother, William Nelson, who ran the farming operations at "Oakland." With the help of servants, she tended chickens, hogs, ducks, and turkeys, preserves food, and handled other household tasks. Some of Elizabeth's letters to Thomas include attached letters from other relatives to Elizabeth such as Frank Page, her oldest son.
In addition to her correspondence with Thomas Nelson Page, Elizabeth's papers include letters from her school days at Long Branch written to her father, Thomas Nelson; letters from her son, Frank Page and his wife, Letitia Rives (Morris) Page, writing from Waco, Texas, where he served as an Episcopal priest in 1890 and in 1911 as a priest in Brooklyn, N. Y.; a 1877 letter from her brother, Robert Nelson, while serving as a missionary in China; an 1865 letter from Anne Wickham, a niece of Elizabeth, concerning the Civil War and her feeling that Jefferson Davis had no role in the assassination of Abraham Lincoln; and several letters to Elizabeth in 1888 expressing sympathy over the death of Anne Seddon (Bruce) Page, Thomas Nelson Page's first wife.
Series 4 begins with the diary of Robert Nelson (1819-1886) kept initially while serving as an Episcopal missionary in Shanghai, China, in 1878, as an account book for a children's school; then kept in Woodbury, Conn., during the last years of his life and that of his wife, Rose (Points) Nelson, whose picture and obituary appear on p. 108 of the volume. Robert Nelson was a brother of Elizabeth Burwell (Nelson) Page.
Diary entries from 1885 to 1886 note Robert's church-related activities, including the number of baptisms, illnesses of church members, attendance at Episcopal conferences, and descriptions of his sermons. On page 90, Robert talks about his participation as a minister in Ulysses Simpson Grant's funeral, and on page 59, Robert laments the low nature of his annual salary of $600.00 in 1885. He gives much information about his family's daily life, travels, illnesses, and birthdays. His children's attendance at school and careers are also mentioned. A trip to Virginia, including to "Oakland," and Charlottesville, are discussed on pages 109-111.
Robert Nelson's correspondence, 1851-1886, was mostly written from or addressed to Shanghai, China, where Nelson served as a missionary. Included are interesting and detailed descriptions of Chinese customs, his family's activities, the burning of his chapel and people stealing all the chapel furnishings, baptism of Chinese people, and the children's school Nelson ran. One letter from Nelson to his sister, Virginia Lafayette (Nelson) Nelson of Charlottesville, concerns a female student whose family threatens to break her legs because she is a Christian.
Robert Nelson's miscellaneous papers include a resolution, 1881, by the Committee for the Shanghai Temperance Society. It honors Nelson for his service on the eve of his departure from China to live the remainder of his life in Connecticut.
Series 5 contains the papers of Rose (Points) Nelson (1827-1885), including correspondence, undated-1870, containing a partial letter (n.d.) from Rose's daughter, Mary C. Nelson, while Mary was traveling by ship towards Yokohama, Japan; and a letter (1870) of Rose's to Mary C. Nelson giving general advice on life as Mary left their home in Shanghai, China, to go to the United States.
Rose Nelson's papers also include parts of a diary written probably in 1865 while she was at "Oakland," Hanover County, Va. In the diary she discusses her children and family activities, the death of Mr. Lincoln, whom she compared to Herod, her glowing opinion of the slaves, and how people are avoiding taking the oath of allegiance; and a narrative, 1865, concerning the death of her son, William Nelson.
Series 6 includes papers of Francis Page (1848-1918). His correspondence, 1877-1910, includes a 1903(?) letter to his brother, Rosewell Page, concerning the beginning of his ministry at St. John's Church, Brooklyn, N.Y., and letters to his other brother, Thomas Nelson Page, congratulating Tom and Anne Seddon (Bruce) Page, Tom's first wife, on their first anniversary and congratulating Tom in 1893 on his second marriage to Florence (Lathrop) Field Page, telling Tom of his call to St. John's Church, asking Tom if he knows anything about the church, and discussing family news, including in 1911 how Frank is coping with the loss of his first wife, Letitia Rives (Morris) Page (better known as Lettie).
Francis Page's legal papers, 1961, include incomplete affidavits related to Frank Page and J. Packard Laird, Jr., concerning property in Hanover County, Va. Frank's heirs are listed.
Thomas Nelson Page (1853-1922) materials appear in Series 7. Correspondence, 1861-1922 (1,305 items) is arranged in chronological order, with undated materials appearing first. Fans of Page's works wrote letters commenting on his writing and his lectures and asking for autographs, biographical sketches of Page, new articles to print in their magazines, or permission to reprint portions of his work. Friends wrote to arrange meetings and trips, and some wrote their condolences at the death of his first wife, Anne Seddon (Bruce) Page, in 1888. For charitable causes people ask Page to donate money or to autograph copies of his books. Notable correspondents include William Gillette, an actor and playwright, Joseph Forney Johnston, a governor of Alabama and a U.S. Senator, Herbert Putnam, Librarian of Congress from 1899-1939, and his second wife, Florence (Lathrop) Field Page.
Most letters from 1861-1887 are written to Tom in Hanover County, Va., Richmond, or Charlottesville. From 1861-1877 most of the correspondence is business-related as Tom was a practicing lawyer in his early adult years, but there is scattered correspondence from family and friends, including his first wife, Annie. One business letter concerns Tom's efforts to buy a farm in Hanover County, Va. In the 1880s his correspondence becomes more numerous as he continues to reside in Hanover County and Richmond practicing law and beginning to receive fan letters for "Marse Chan," one of his early stories first appearing in 1884 in the Century Magazine and published in a collection in 1887. In 1886 Tom and Annie are married and some letters to Tom are written to him aboard ship headed for England where they spent their honeymoon. Also, in 1886, Rosewell Page, Tom's younger brother, writes to him about his law practice in Danville, Va. Thomas Nelson Carter, Tom's law partner in the firm of Page and Carter, Richmond, Va., writes Tom in 1887 while Tom is on a trip to Brussels. Carter congratulates him on his writing and discusses a Richmond group of writers called The Skaerl. Tom writes Carter from St. Paul, Minn., talking about his travel and investments. Over the years that Tom travels or lives away from Virginia, Carter helps to keep the law practice going in Richmond and helps Tom with his financial concerns. (After Tom marries the second time to Florence (Lathrop) Field Page, the partnership is dissolved and Tom devotes the rest of his life to writing, donating time and money to charitable causes, and serving as U.S. Ambassador to Italy during World War I.)
Also, in 1887, most of the correspondence comes from fans wanting Tom to lecture in their towns, thanking him for assisting them in critiquing their writing, asking for help in getting their works published, wanting copies of his work, wanting articles written by Tom to publish in university publications, newspapers, and magazines, and asking for autographs. One publisher expresses his disappointment that Tom goes to another publisher. Unrelated to his writing there are occasional business letters, including a telegram in which a gentleman wants to invest in Page's iron works.
Beginning in 1888, Tom and Annie write frequently while she spends time with her parents at "Staunton Hill," Charlotte County, Va., or while Tom travels frequently on speaking tours. Tom shares some news of his legal schedule, Richmond news, and how he misses her. On September 4, 1888, Tom writes "Law is dull. Indeed, I do not know what I should do without my Literary side-shows from time to time." While traveling in Georgia on August 2, 1888, Tom talks about his meeting and impressions of Joel Chandler Harris. On August 31, 1888, Tom writes Annie that he is trying to get Two Little Confederates ready to return to Charles Scribner. Fans continue to correspond with Tom praising In Ole Virginia in which appears "Marse Chan," and asking him to lecture in locations such as Charlottesville, Staunton, and Richmond, all in Va., Louisville, Ky., Washington, D. C., Baltimore, Md., New York, N.Y., and Tennessee. Henry Woodfin Grady, a friend of Tom's, requests that Tom come to do readings in Atlanta, and Charles Scribner communicates with Tom about publishing his writings.
Annie died in December 1888, and thus much of the extant correspondence for this year includes sympathy letters to Tom. Family and friends extend their sympathies at his loss, but also, complete strangers write from around the United States.
From January through March, 1889, numerous people continue to send their sympathies from the United States and abroad. Richard Malcolm Johnston, a Georgia lawyer, author, and educator who idealized the South as Tom did, offers his condolences and talks about his readings on the lecture circuit with Mark Twain. In this January 23rd letter, Richard writes, "We had an excellent audience. I never saw Mark so fine. It was most generous in [sic] him to volunteer to come to my help." Tom was to have been Richard's lecture partner but Clemens filled in for Tom who canceled due to the death of Annie. James Burton Pond, in February and March, corresponds with Tom during this sad time. He served as a general agent and manager for numerous writers and musicians. In February, an artist from Washington, D.C., A. G. Keaton, is arranging the details for a portrait he is doing of Annie. (In July and August, F. R. Pustet and Co., New York, N.Y., converses with Tom about a stained glass window being made as a memorial for Annie.)
By April, 1889, Tom began to receive more business-related correspondence. Johnston wrote more often, encouraging Tom to enter a new lecture arrangement with Pond. Hilgard Tyndale of Charles Scribner's Sons discussed the play he was writing based on "Marse Chan" (3/10/89 and 4/4/89). Several colleges invited him to visit. J. M. Stoddart with Lippincott's Monthly Magazine notified Tom on April 2nd that he would receive $400.00 for two articles he had written, while D. Lothrop Company of Boston wanted Tom to write a short serial. Molly Elliott Seawell, a fellow author, seemed to see Tom as a mentor and asked for advice on her writing.
To help assuage Tom's sorrow, Rosewell and Tom traveled in Europe in July and August of 1889. Thomas Nelson Carter, Tom's law partner, kept them abreast of Richmond news and mentioned possible investments (7/24/89 and 8/19/89). Fans continued to write asking questions about his writings, requesting copies of his works, and asking for writing advice. In August, Sally Page (Nelson) Hughes, daughter of William Nelson of "Midway," Mecklenburg County, Va., gave Tom her personal reminiscences of Michel Ney, also known as Peter Stuart Ney.
Tom lived with Rosewell in Richmond during 1890-1891 except for when he has away on business, especially in Kentucky. He traveled briefly in England during this time also. Family letters include letters from Annie's mother, Sarah Alexander (Seddon) Bruce (5/7/91 and 11/4/91), Thomas Jefferson Page, a Southern expatriate living in Florence, Italy, (1/12/90 and 2/26/90), his aunt, Anne Rose Page, who lived much of her life at "Oakland," Hanover County, Va., and his uncle, William Nelson, who was the manager of "Oakland," asking for financial assistance (3/18/91). (There is much correspondence between Tom and his mother, Elizabeth; it appears in Series 3. Likewise, correspondence with his father, John, appears in Series 2; there is much less of this correspondence.)Publishers continued to write Tom, including Warwick House, an English publisher writing about royalties; Ward, Lock, Boyden and Co., London, trying to defend their handling of the sales of In Ole Virginia; and The Christian Union, New York, concerning revising a paper Tom has written. Much of the correspondence in these years, however, came from fans and friends who praised Tom and his works asking again for biographical sketches of him, thanking him for speaking to their group, encouraging Tom to write a history of the South, wanting autographs, and inviting him to visit their homes while he is on the lecture circuit. Almost all of Tom's fan mail is positive except for two negative letters (one dated 10/31/91) from a fundamentalist concerning how Tom rendered a verse from the Bible. William G. Eggleston of The Chicago Herald wanted help with using black dialect (5/31/90). A few letters illustrate Tom's philanthropic nature, as in November 1890, someone wrote to ask him to become a member of the Maury Memorial Commission. He raised money for the Richmond Public Library; Joseph Reid Anderson sent Tom a contribution for the library on March 2, 1891.
A baroness in France and Tom began corresponding in 1891. There are six letters starting on March 11 concerning Alexandre Marie Quesnay de Beaurepaire, who wanted to establish an academy of arts and sciences in Richmond after the American Revolution. Baroness Yetta Blaze de Bury asked for Tom's assistance in finding more information about Quesnay de Beaurepaire. She also commented on another of Tom's works, On Newfound River.
In 1892 Tom continued to live in Richmond, Va., as a bachelor in-between frequent travels for speaking engagements. Friends invited Tom to visit with them when he spoke in places such as New York, Alabama, and Texas, while fans wrote to ask him to speak at schools in Louisville, Ky., Winchester, Ky., and Roanoke, Va. or to speak at clubs like the Southern Club of Harvard, to provide complimentary passes at clubs like the Union League Club of Chicago when he visited in that city, to help them with their writing aspirations, and to praise On Newfound River and The Old South.
Tom's life changed when he married Florence (Lathrop) Field Page on June 6, 1893. After that time, his visits Washington, D.C., New York City, and York Harbor, Maine, but throughout his marriage Florence and Tom traveled every year overseas. Frequent letters from Rosewell kept Tom abreast of matters at "Oakland," including comments on how Tom's works were in demand in Richmond bookstores, news of neighbors and friends, and family activity such as their mother's giving Christmas presents to white and black workers at "Oakland" or their father's discussion about where he was on Christmas Eve during each year of the Civil War (12/24/94). Rosewell discussed investments, selling family land in Hanover County, Va., Tom's tenant, Edmund T. Taylor, at "Mont Air," Hanover County, Va., the status of crops, horses, and livestock, and Tom's opinion of Uncle Tom's Cabin as discussed in The Atlanta Evening News (1/16/01). Edmund T. Taylor, Tom's tenant farmer in Bandana, Va., wrote Tom in August and September of 1901 about the corn, potato, and wheat crop and the livestock, sent a drawing of a barn that he wanted Tom to approve, and discussed rebuilding bridges in Hanover County, Va., washed out by high water. Tom's letters to his family in Virginia are rarely found in Mss1P1465aFA2 but his letter of May 17, 1893 to Rosewell was written prior to going on his honeymoon aboard a steamer to London. Tom enclosed a check to provide for contingencies at "Oakland" and urged Rosewell, if necessary, to contact Thomas Nelson Carter, Tom's power-of-attorney and law partner, for stocks to be sold to provide emergency monies for the homestead.
Business letters came from a lawyer in Charlottesville, Va., concerning land Tom wished to buy (7/28/93), Ward, Lock and Bowden, a publisher in London, with an attached agreement concerning publishing of Tom's works in England (7/14/94), Charles Scribner discussing publishing schedules, royalties, and a contract for Polly (10/31/94 and 2/11/95) actually published earlier in In Ole Virginia in 1887, J. Cabell Brockenbrough concerning translating Tom's work into French (8/23/95), Sol Smith Russell concerning critiquing Tom's plays (7/17/96), and Elizabeth Marbury of New York who was trying to submit Red Rock to playwrights and managers but is not having any luck (1/29/01). Tom received correspondence from the various clubs he was a member of in Washington, D.C., such as the Chevy Chase Club (9/13/00). Over the years he served as an officer in these clubs and helped with renovations and fund-raising. John Stewart Bryan, writing for his father Joseph Bryan who was ill, wrote several letters in 1900 concerning stock in the Lake Superior Co. Occasionally Tom received mundane letters about his Washington, D.C., home at No. 1759 R Street. Some refer to repairs needed on his property. In October 1900, his insurance agent sent a list with evaluations of the contents of this home. Like most folks with ample financial means, Tom frequently received fund-raising letters. For example, a feeder school to the University of Virginia located at Morrisville, Va., requested money in December 1902.
Friends and fans continued to write with high praises for one of Tom's latest works, Red Rock, wanting to know if his fiction was based on actual events, or writing to share similar stories of black slaves. Ellen Shields of Natchez, Miss., inspired by Tom's viewpoint, discussed a sketch of a black carpenter who worked for her father on their plantations and who liked to preach (7/2/00). The editor of The Philadelphia Item asked Tom's opinion about British and American reviewers (8/18/00).
Distant family members and sometimes unrelated folks wrote Tom for political influence and financial assistance. B. M. Fontaine did not want to become further indebted to Tom, and Joseph Reid Anderson Bruce, a nephew by marriage, wanted some help in getting a job (9/17/00). In June 1900, A. L. Nelson wished Tom could help finance a distant relative's education at the University of Virginia. A cousin in Naples, Florida, requested Tom's aid in getting someone into the U.S. Naval Academy (2/12/03), while Frank Nelson, Jr., thanked Tom for money loaned to him at Virginia Polytechnic Institute.
From 1904-1908, Tom's correspondence again was an even mix of fan letters and business letters. Fund-raising letters abound with several requests for complete sets of his printed works to be donated to various libraries in Virginia, for money to renovate an Episcopal church, or for money to pay for medical treatment of indigent persons. Marie von Unschuld at the University of Music and Dramatic Art in D.C. wrote for Tom's financial assistance in establishing scholarships for her students (7/18/04). Tom received mail from agricultural researchers about alfalfa experiments and inoculating leguminous plants and from the U.S. Department of Agriculture concerning the building of a road near Beaverdam in Hanover County, Va.